<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Monologue, or Soliloquy on the Annuals</title>
            <author>
               <name>John Wilson</name>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <name>Laura Mandell</name>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1829-12</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>TEI formatted filesize uncompressed: approx. 28 kbytes</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>King Library, Miami University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Oxford, OH</pubPlace>
            <date>2004-06-26</date>
            <availability status="unknown">
               <p> Miami University makes a claim of copyright only to original contributions
                        made by the Poetess Archive participants and other members of the university
                        community. Miami University makes no claim of copyright to the original
                        text. Permission is granted to download, transmit or otherwise reproduce,
                        distribute or display the contributions to this work claimed by Miami
                        University for non-profit educational purposes, provided that this header is
                        included in its entirety. For inquiries about commercial uses, please
                        contact laura.mandell@gmail.com. </p>
            </availability>
            <idno>wilson1829</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>The Poetess Archive: an Electronic Collection</title>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Laura Mandell,</name>
               <resp>General Editor.</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>
                     <name>John Wilson</name>
                  </author>
                  <title level="a" type="main">Monologue, </title>
                  <title level="a" type="subordinate">or Soliloquy on the Annuals</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Blackwood's Edinburgh Review</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">26 </biblScope>
                     <date>1829-12</date>
                     <biblScope unit="page">948-976 </biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>This document follows the rules specified for TEI use by NINES.</p>
            <p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been transcribed as entity
                    references.</p>
            <p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
            <p>Because of web browser variability, all colons and hyphens have been typed on the
                    U.S. keyboard; dashes have been rendered as two hyphens.</p>
            <p>Special characters (letters with accents, etc.) have been coded according to
                    Unicode rather than as entity references.</p>
            <p>Page numbers appear at the beginning of each page, no matter where originally
                    placed.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title>"Monologue, or Soliloquy on the Annuals"</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <name>John Wilson</name>
            </byline>
            <p>[In <biblStruct>
                  <monogr>
                     <title>Blackwood's Edinburgh Magazine</title>
                     <imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
                        <date>1829-12</date>
                        <biblScope unit="page">948-976</biblScope>
                     </imprint>
                  </monogr>
               </biblStruct>] </p>
            <p>PERIODICAL Literature — how sweet is the name! ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: We omit an extended riff praising the annuals by metaphorically equating them with plants and flowers.</note> We often pity our poor ancestors. ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: This sentence about having nothing to do may confuse readers because of its use of the phrase'make ends meet' for gratifying interest..</note> What a weary waste must have seemed expanding before their eyes between
                    morning and night! ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: one sentence for emphasis</note> True, ladies sighed not then for periodicals — but there, in the depths
                    of their ignorance, lay their utter wretchedness....<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: omitted sentence offsets passage's parallel structure</note> True that many sat all life-long at needle-work; but is not that a very
                    sew-sew sort of life? Then oh! the miserable males! We speak of times after the
                    invention, it is true, of printing — but who read what were called books
                    then? Books! no more like our periodicals, than dry, rotten, worm-eaten, fungous
                    logs are like green living leafy trees, laden with dews, bees, and birds, in the
                    musical sunshine. What could males do then but yawn, sleep, snore, guzzle,
                    guttle, and drink till they grew dead and got buried?...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: a passage about fox hunting as a passtime.</note>
                    [D]eath itself is no relief to the dulness; a funeral is little better...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: clause about types of burial</note> ; along with
                    the sables is worn a suitable stupidity by all the sad survivors – And such,
                    before the era of Periodicals, such was life in merry England. Oh! dear! – oh!
                    dear me! </p>
            <p>...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: aside attacking The Quarterly</note>[I]n the
                    times we allude to (don’t mention dates) there was little or no reading in
                    England. There was neither the Reading Fly nor the Reading Public. What could
                    this be owing to, but the non-existence of periodicals? What elderly-young lady
                    could be expected to turn from house affairs, for example, to Spenser's Fairy
                        Queen?...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: description of the Fairy Queen</note>
                    As to Shakespeare, we cannot find many traces of him in the domestic occupations
                    of the English gentry during the times alluded to ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: aside about Hamlet</note> . We have Mr
                    Wordsworth's authority for believing that Paradise Lost was a dead letter, and
                    John Milton virtually anonymous. We need say no more. Books like these, huge
                    heavy vols. lay with other lumber in garrets and libraries. As yet, periodical
                    literature was not; and the art of printing seems long to have preceded the art
                    of reading. It did not occur to those generations that books were intended to be
                    read by people in general, but only by the select few. Whereas now, reading is
                    not only one of the luxuries, but absolutely one of the necessaries of life, and
                    we no more think of going without our book than without our breakfast;...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: phrase containing an obscure allusion to Welsh rarebit</note> — Thomas Campbell and Thomas Mo[o]re sweeten tea for us —...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor"/>
                    .</p>
            <p>We have not time ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: confusing sentence structure</note> to trace the history of the great revolution. But a great revolution there
                    has been, from nobody’s reading anything, to everybody’s reading all things; and
                    perhaps it began with that good old proser Richardson. He set the public
                    a-reading, and Fielding Smollett shoved her on — till the Minerva Press
                    took her in hand — and then — the Periodicals. But such Periodicals!
                        <title level="j">The Gentleman's Magazine </title>—God bless it then,
                    now, and forever!— <title level="j">the Monthly Review</title>, <title level="j">the Critical</title> and <title level="j">the British
                        Critic</title>! The age had been for some years literary, and was now fast
                    becoming periodical. Magazines multiplied. Arose in glory <title level="j">the
                        Edinburgh</title>, and then <title level="j">the Quarterly Review</title>
                    — <title level="j">Maga</title>,<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <bibl>
                     <title level="j">Blackwood's Edinburgh Review</title> was also called
                                <hi rend="it">Maga</hi>;</bibl> it is the periodical in which this
                        essay appears. [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note> like a new sun, looked out
                    from heaven ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: extended                         metaphor</note>
                    —and last of all, "the Planetary Five," the Annuals,<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">Also called <soCalled>Gift Books</soCalled>,
                        collections of poetry published annually and lavishly embellished were the
                        major medium for publication of poetess poetry (see <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>Cynthia Lawford</name>
                     </author>, "Bijoux Beyond Possession: The Prima Donnas of L.E.L.'s Album
                            Poems," and <author>
                        <name>Paula Feldman</name>
                     </author>
                  </bibl>, "The Poet and the Profits: Felicia Hemans and the Literary
                        Marketplace," in <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>Armstrong</name>
                     </author> and <author>
                        <name>Blain</name>
                     </author>, <title level="m">Women’s Poetry, Late Romantic to late
                                Victorian,</title>
                  </bibl> 102-114 and 71-101, respectively. [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note>
                    hung their lamps on high; other similar luminous bodies emerged from the clouds,
                    till the whole circumference was bespangled, and astronomy became the favourite
                    study with all ranks of people, from the King upon the throne to the meanest of
                    his subjects. Now, will any one presume to deny, that this has been a great
                    change to the better, and that there is now something worth living for in the
                    world? Look at our literature now, and it is all periodical together. A thousand
                    daily, thrice-a-week, twice-a-week, weekly newspapers, a hundred monthlies,
                    fifty quarterlies, and twenty-five annuals! No mouth looks up now and is not
                    fed; on the contrary, we are now in danger of being crammed; an empty head is as
                    rare as an empty stomach; the whole day is one meal, one physical, moral, and
                    intellectual feast; the Public goes to bed with a Periodical in her hand, and
                    falls asleep with it beneath her pillow. </p>
            <p>What blockhead thinks now of reading Milton, or Pope, or Gray? <title> Paradise
                        Lost </title> is lost; it has gone to the devil. Pope's Epistles are
                    returned to the dead-letter office; the age is too loyal for <quote>"ruin seize
                        thee, ruthless king,"</quote>
               <note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <hi>
                     <quote>"ruin seize thee, ruthless king"</quote>
                  </hi>: Wilson quotes the first line of <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>Thomas Gray,</name>
                     </author>
                     <title level="a">The Bard</title>
                     <date>(1757)</date>.</bibl> [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note> and the
                    oldest inhabitant has forgotten <quote>"the curfew tolls."</quote>
               <note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <hi>
                     <quote>"the curfew tolls"</quote>
                  </hi>: these are the first three words of the first line of <bibl>
                     <title level="a">Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard</title> by <author>
                        <name>Gray</name>
                     </author>
                     <date>(1751)</date>.</bibl> [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note>
            </p>
            <p>All the great geniuses of the day are Periodical. The Scotch Novels — the
                    Irish Novels — the English Novels — the American Novels — the
                    Family Library — the Library of Useful and Entertaining Knowledge —
                    Napier's History of the Spanish War — Tytler's History of Scotland —
                    Chalmers's Civic Economy — But what is the need of enumeration —
                    every work worth reading is published in numbers ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: enumeration of titles as examples</note> .</p>
            <p>What Donkey was the first to bray that the Annuals, the subject of this our
                    Monologue, were introduced into this country from Germany? Gentle reader, did
                    you ever see a German Annual, or Literary Almanack? ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: direct satire</note> . But you know better —
                    you know that the Annuals are a native growth of the soil of England, springing
                    up like white and red clover beneath lime (a curious fact that) wherever the
                    periodical ploughshare has drawn its furrows. ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: extended metaphor</note>
            </p>
            <p>But lo! arrayed in figure of a fan, and gorgeous as spread-peacocktail —
                    the Annuals! ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: extended metaphor</note> They have
                    formed themselves into classes beneath our touch — according to some fine
                    affinities of name and nature; and behold in one Triad, the <title level="j">Forget-me-Not </title>, the <title level="j">Souvenir </title>, and the
                        <title level="j">Keepsake</title>. </p>
            <p>One word embraces them all — Memorials. When <quote>"absent long and
                        distant far,"</quote>
               <note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <hi>
                     <quote>"absent long and distant far"</quote>
                  </hi>: Wilson quotes <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>Anne Home Hunter</name>
                        <name>(Mrs. John Hunter)</name>
                     </author>, <title level="a">La Douce Chimère</title> (line 29), <title level="m">Poems</title>
                     <date>(1802)</date>.</bibl> [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note> the
                    living, lovely, loving, and beloved, how often are they utterly forgotten! But
                    let something that once was theirs suddenly meet our eyes, and in a moment,
                    returning from the region of the rising or the setting sun, lo! the friend of
                    our youth is at our side, unchanged his voice and his smile; and dearer to our
                    eyes than ever, because of some slight, faint, and affecting change wrought on
                    face and figure by climate and by years! Let it be but his name written with his
                    own hand, on the title-page of a book; or a few syllables on the margin of a
                    favourite passage which long ago we may have read together, <quote>"when life
                        itself was new,"</quote>
               <note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <hi>
                     <quote>"when life itself was new"</quote>
                  </hi>: Wilson quotes <bibl>
                     <title level="a">The Old Man’s Song</title> by <author>
                        <name>James Montgomery</name>
                     </author>, co-author of <title level="m">Poems on the Abolition of the
                                Slave Trade</title>
                     <date>(1809)</date>
                  </bibl>. [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note> and poetry overflowed the whole
                    world! Or a lock of her hair in whose eyes we first knew the meaning of the word
                        <soCalled>depth</soCalled> applied to the human soul, or the celestial sky!
                    But oh! if death hath stretched out and out into the dim arms of eternity the
                    distance — and removed away into that bourne from which no traveller
                        returns<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <hi>and removed away into that bourne from which no traveller returns</hi>:
                        Wilson's phrase comes from <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>William Shakespeare</name>
                     </author>
                     <title>Hamlet</title> III.i.78-79:</bibl>
                  <quote>"The undiscover’d country, from whose bourn / No traveller
                            returns."</quote> [Poetess Archive Editor.] </note> the absence —
                    of her on whose forehead once hung the relic we adore in our despair —
                    what heart may abide the beauty of the ghost that, as at the touch of a
                    talisman, doth sometimes at midnight appear before our sleepless bed, and with
                    pale uplifted arms waft over us — so momentary is the vision — at
                    once a blessing and a farewell! </p>
            <p>But we must be cheerful, for these are cheerful volumes, and they are bound in
                    smiles. Yet often <quote>"cheerful thoughts bring sad thoughts to the
                        mind,"</quote>
               <note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <hi>
                     <quote>"cheerful thoughts bring sad thoughts to the mind,"</quote>
                  </hi>: Wilson quotes <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>William Wordworth</name>
                     </author>, <title level="a">Lines Written in Early Spring</title>,
                                <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title>
                     <date>(1798)</date>
                  </bibl>: <quote>"In that sweet mood when pleasant thoughts / Bring sad
                            thoughts to the mind."</quote> [Poetess Archive Editor.]</note> and the
                    eye slides away insensibly from the sunshine to the cloud-shadows, feeling that
                    they are bound together in beauty by one spirit ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor"/> . </p>
            <p>But come — this will never do; we shall never, at this rate, get to the
                    Annuals. Now, then, for the </p>
            <p>FORGET-ME-NOT.</p>
            <p>The name is a good one and belongs, we believe, to a pretty little flower of a
                    truly poetical character, that loves to smile in the shade. Forget-me-Not! why
                    there is no fear — no danger at least, of that, my love; yet were we to
                    forget thee, for an hour in the day, or a day in the week, where would be the
                    harm? ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: extended metaphor</note> Mr Ackerman, you
                    are one of the best bibliopoles — Mr Shoberl, though your name is hard to
                    pronounce, you are a most worthy editor. ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: reviews of particular pieces in this collection</note> — Shaded in the solitary arbour there sits, with her lyre laid on roses
                    by her side, the dark-haired Improvisatrice; and we who never saw her face,
                    though we have in numerous verses seen her very soul, cannot but have a dream of
                    L. E. L. ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: reviews continue of particular pieces</note>
            </p>
            <p>Not much poetry, we observe, in <title level="j">the Forget-me-Not</title>
                    — so much, perhaps, the better; yet what there is, is either agreeable,
                    curious, or good; or all the three in one, such as the lines by Francis Jeffrey,
                    written originally in a lady's album. ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: poem reprinted</note> — Barry Cornwall<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">
                  <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>
                           <anchor xml:id="cornwall"/>Barry Cornwall</name>
                     </author>
                  </bibl> is the pseudonym for <bibl>
                     <author>
                        <name>Bryan Procter</name>
                     </author>
                  </bibl>, a name that Wilson uses subsequently, although he erroneously
                        spells it "<hi>Proctor</hi>." [Poetess Archive Editor.]</note> often writes
                    beautifully — but why will he persist in being ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor"/> so Cockneyish? ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: poem reprinted</note> [I]f a man who is privileged
                    to drink of the pure waters of Helicon<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">"Helicon" is the name of a mountain in Boeotia
                        sacred to the Muses (O.E.D.) [Poetess Archive Editor.]</note> prefer
                    dabbling his lips in the puddle of the New River,<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">The New River is a river in London, tributary
                        to the Thames, at this time providing the metropolis with water; see
                        BOPCRIS: "New River." [Poetess Archive Editor.]</note> there seems to be no
                    help for it. 'Tis distressing to hear him who can sing like a nightingale,
                    screeching like a sparrow with a sore throat. <ref target="#cornwall">
                  <name>Mr Proctor</name>
               </ref> will pardon us, but we grieve to see him the only Cockney in the
                    Collection. We are very angry; for we never entirely lose our temper with any
                    poet whose genius has not, in its happier moments, given us delight. As for Lord
                    Byron's boyish verses ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: evaluation of those verses</note> ; what an
                    absurdity it is for a man of sense, taste, and judgment, like Mr Shoberl, to
                    suppose that any value can be given to his volume by [adding] such verses as the
                    weakest, worst, and most worthless of "Poems by a Minor"<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">Wilson misrembers the title: <bibl>
                     <hi>Hours of Idleness</hi>
                     <date>(1807)</date>;</bibl> Byron responded to criticism of the volume
                        by writing and publishing <bibl>
                     <title level="a">English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</title>
                     <date>(1809)</date>.</bibl> [Poetess Archive Editor.]</note> when we all
                    know that, with one or two exceptions, Byron was ashamed of the very best of
                    them; and that even the very best afforded no intimation of his future genius,
                    which was the sudden growth of his inspired manhood. — Miss Jewesbury's
                    "Lines on Receiving a Bunch of Flowers from the Author of the
                        <title>Excursion</title>" are worthy of the subject, — and so
                    beautiful, indeed, that with them we must adorn our Number.</p>
            <p>...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: poem printed</note>
            </p>
            <p> We have no room to praise, and no inclination to abuse, any body else in the <hi rend="it"> the Forget-me-Not </hi>...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor"/> . It has long had, and long will have, a deservedly extensive circulation
                    — its embellishments are beautiful — and the whole volume inspired
                    by a benign spirit of humanity, which disposes us to think with much esteem and
                    regard of Publisher, Editor, and Contributors, even the stupidest among them,
                    — and that some of them are pretty stupid in their own way, it would be
                    hypocrisy to conceal, and impudence to deny; but we see no reason why a little
                    occasional and temporary stupidity should not be as excusable in Ackerman's
                        <title level="j">Forget-me-Not </title>, as in <title level="j">Blackwood's
                        Magazine</title>. ...<note place="foot" resp="Poetess Archive Editor">editorial truncation: other annuals reviewed</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <head>
            <hi>Notes</hi>
         </head>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
